So today's דף *Daf* is מ"ג *Mem Gimmel*. We'll be making up
the as of a bit behind on שבת *Shabbos*. Today's דף *Daf*
is מ"ג *Mem Gimmel* and we pick up from the bottom of
מ"ב עמוד ב' *Mem Bais Amud Bais* and we were talking about
how you do the making and the testing of the תכלת techeiles
*Techelet* to not invalidate. So we are five lines from the bottom
near the end of the line. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*.
תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*, תכלת techeiles אין לה בדיקה ein
la bedikah ואינה נקנית אלא מן המומחה min ha-mumcheh. *Techelet ein lah
bedika ve'einah nikneis ela min hamumche*. There is no way to do
בדיקה bdika *bedika* for תכלת techeiles *Techelet*. That's what we think it
means. There's no way to actually run a test. So גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to challenge that one back. We thought that you
did run a test. Anyway, and therefore you can only take it
from an expert because you don't want somebody to be selling you
the קלא אילן kala ilan *Kala Ilan*, the fake תכלת techeiles. *Techelet*.
מומחה mumcheh *Mumche* does not just mean somebody who knows what they're
doing and is an expert. It also means somebody you can trust,
somebody who has a standing in the community who you can trust,
you know, trust them. This is why people don't use תכלת techeiles.
*Techelet* these days for that because of that? No, they don't use
it because we weren't able to identify it for a long time.
Okay. תפילין tefillin, יש להם בדיקה *Tefillin yesh lahem bedika*. תפילין tefillin.
*Tefillin* have בדיקה *bedika*. But that's not how רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* puts
it, right?
The מומחה mumcheh *mumche* is someone that knows that קלא אילן kala
ilan *Kala Ilan* is אסור *assur*. Right. Not to חס ושלום *chas
veshalom* somebody start to teach it.
Right. I mean, but we've already introduced the idea. Right. That's true.
If you get the chance,
I'd love to talk about תכלת techeiles *Techelet* one day.
Yeah. Okay. Right. So, yeah, but since he... so he knows it's
אסור *assur*, right. But I'm saying the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before clearly
was aware and was concerned about people that were that were deceptive.
So I would say, you know, here it's also that מומחה mumcheh.
*mumche* means also knows but can be trusted. Now, תפילין tefillin יש
להם בדיקה *Tefillin yesh lahem bedika*. תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* can be tested.
Maybe also we'll discuss need to be tested, you know, about opening
up תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. We'll talk about that. But you can see
whether practically it was written correctly. ואינן נקנין אלא מן המומחה min
ha-mumcheh *Ve'einan niknin ela min hamumche*. Nevertheless, you can only get it
from a מומחה mumcheh *mumche*. Why? Meaning a סופר מומחה mumcheh *sopher
mumche*? Yeah. Because just because it looks correct in terms of the
כתב *ksav* doesn't mean everything was done correctly. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says,
for example, maybe the עיבוד *ibud* was not done לשמה lishmah *lishma*.
Maybe some things that are not discernible to the eye were not
done correctly. So therefore it needs to be an expert who knows
what the הלכות halachos *halachos* are and again with the assumption here
that people are also honest. But different people.
In other words, the person that does the hide and the person
who writes it.
Well, that's true. Maybe it is and maybe it's also that we're
assuming that you're getting it from that because this person knows the
laws and he's now selling you your כשר kasher. *kasher* תפילין tefillin,
*Tefillin* that he also checked up earlier up on the on the
thing. Okay. Now, ספרים Sfarim? ומזוזות יש להם בדיקה וניקחין מכל אדם
*Sefarim u'mezuzot yesh lahem bedika ve'nikchin mi'kol adam*. ספרים *Sefarim* and מזוזות
*mezuzot* can also be checked that they were written correctly and they
can be purchased from anyone. Why is it different? So presumably it's
different because רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says you don't need עיבוד לשמה lishmah
*ibud lishma*. So there's nothing that's not discernible to the naked eye.
Of course the question is, well what do you mean? I mean,
don't you maybe you don't need עיבוד לשמה lishmah *ibud lishma*, don't
you need כתיבה לשמה lishma *ksiva lishma*? Is everything really discernible? But
anyways that's what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. If you take a look
at תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*, there's a great תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* here for
a couple of reasons. תפילין tefillin יש להם בדיקה *Tefillin yesh lahem
bedika*, says תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*. פשיטא pshita בקדשאי בחסירה ויתירה *Peshutah b'kadshai
b'chaseira v'yesira*. ואפילו אינך מן המומחה לא אבדן ונידבעינן עיבוד לשמה *ve'afilu
einach min hamumche lo avdan unidevainan ibud lishma*. אבל ספרים ומזוזות לא
בעינן עיבוד לשמה *aval sefarim u'mezuzot lo bayinan ibud lishma*. And then
he says, וכן פירש הרב משה בר מיימון *vechein peirush haRav Moshe
Bar Maimon* שבמזוזה לא בעי לשמה *she'bimzuza lo bay lishma* ולא פירש
מנא ליה *velo peirush mena ley* ושמא מהכא *veshema mehacha*. So there
are very few תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* in ש"ס *Shas* that quote the
רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*. Here it quotes the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* and he
says, oh the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* but he writes it like the
רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* was like a בעל תוספות Tosafot *Baal Tosfos* or
something. פירוש *pirush*, like he had a commentary on the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* but he didn't spell it out. The reason לא פירש מנא
ליה *lo peirush mena ley* is because no פירש מנא ליה *peirush
mena ley* in the entire משנה תורה Torah *Mishneh Torah*. But you
know it's clear it seems like you know what he did was
he had this weird this question: does מזוזה mezuzah, *mezuzah* need לשמה
*lishma*? רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has this weird idea you don't need לשמה
*lishma* by מזוזה mezuzah *mezuzah* and he goes around and he looks
around and he finds, oh the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says the same
thing, you don't need it לשמה *lishma* for מזוזה mezuzah. *mezuzah*, maybe
he's getting it from here. So anyways it's a strange... it's not
strange, but it's a nice and interesting תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* that he
quotes the רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam*, one of the very few that does
it in the ש"ס *Shas*. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says that that's
not true, מזוזה mezuzah *mezuzah* does need לשמה *lishma*. So then what
is the issue? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says that really we're לא
חושש *lo choshesh*, both תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* and מזוזות *mezuzot* need לשמה
*lishma*. We're לא חושש *lo choshesh* that they were not done לשמה
*lishma*. Everybody knows you need the עור לשמה *or lishma*. We're לא
חושש *lo choshesh* that somebody's going to deceive you because of that,
there's not a high profit motive for that, that's not the concern.
The only concern is whether they were technically written correctly. So therefore
the difference between תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* and מזוזות *mezuzot* is whether you
actually want to or are going to open them up. תפילין tefillin.
*Tefillin* because they are sealed, people it's not a nice thing to
be opening them up and therefore as a general rule we don't
overcheck תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin*. But מזוזות *mezuzot* are very easy, you open
it up and you look at it, it's easy to check. So
therefore because תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* you're not going to want to, you're
not supposed to open it too much, you want to make sure
you buy it from an expert so you're not forced to open
it. Whereas in מזוזות *mezuzot* it's not a big deal, you open
it and you check and that leads תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* into a
discussion of how frequently do you have to check your תפילין tefillin.
*Tefillin*, how frequently you have to check your מזוזות *mezuzot*. And interestingly
it's not really in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, mostly תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*
is drawing on some other source. It's twice every seven years for
תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* too? Yeah, although he quotes different opinions about the
תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin* exactly for this reason that you don't want to
open up your תפילין *Tefillin* too much. So by the תפילין *Tefillin*
the question is, you know, maybe even less frequently. Yes.
Here's what I heard, I don't know if this
is
what...
To the
ספרים, what
בדיקה do you need to do for the ספרים? I understand the
מזוזה, mezuzah, what do you
mean, ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah here specifically presumably?
Oh, it's not something like ספרי קודש? Sifrei Kodesh?
Presumably not, although that's a good question. If it were ספרי קודש,
Sifrei Kodesh, it would be a big deal, right? Yeah, so presumably
it means ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. And מזוזה mezuzah they usually say
ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah and תפילין, right?
Right, which is there is no way to test it and that's
one of those things you just have to assume, that's a good
point, right? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, let's take
a look.
Okay, the—so now we're going to talk about the תכלת techeiles which
is our focus. ותכלת אין לה בדיקה, u'techeiles ein la bdika, is
there no way of checking the תכלת techelet. to see whether it's
the genuine
article? והא רב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה בדיק ליה, v'ha Rav Yitzchak
brei d'Rav Yehuda badik lei, he tested it. רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak
son of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda tested it. And how—here's how he
tested it. מייתי, meisi, he brought מגביא גילא, magvia gila, which is
some type of—if you look at רש"י, Rashi בלשון ארמי ספר אלום,
bi'lishon Arami sefer alum, some type of a metal, I guess.
ומיא דשבלילתא u'maya d'shavlilta
and water that was sort of used from some type of a
vegetable,
the water after having cooked certain vegetables,
ומימי רגלים u'meimi raglayim and urine, בן ארבעים יום, ben arbaim yom,
forty days old urine. רש"י Rashi says it means from an infant
that was forty days, but more likely רש"י Rashi says it means
urine that's been for forty days old.
Okay, דף מ"ב עמוד א', daf mem beis amud aleph, starting to
sound like ברכות Berachos now. ותרייה בגווייהו מאורתא ועד צפרא v'saryei be'gavaihu
mei'orta v'ad tzafra and he would let the cloth that had the
absorbed תכלת techelet be submerged in it from the evening until the
next morning. איפרח חזותיה, iprach chazusei, if the color separated, then פסולה,
psula, invalid, you know it's not real תכלת. techeiles, לא איפרח חזותיה,
lo iprach chazusei, if the color did not separate, if the color
held fast even after having gone through this process, then כשרה, kshera,
you know it's תכלת. techeiles. That's his testing. ורב אדא קמיה דרבא
משמיה דרב אויא אמר, v'Rav Adda kamei d'Rava mishmei d'Rav Avya amar,
and now רב אדא Rav Adda has another way of testing it,
which is what's his way? מייתי חמירא ארקסה, meisi chamira arkasa, you
bring this hard yeast,
very sharp
yeast, דסערי d'seari of barley, ואפייה בגוויה v'afyei be'gavei and you cook
it in it, you make חמץ chametz with it, you make bread
with a little bit of this color in it. אישתני למעליותא, ishtani
l'maalyusa, if now it improved,
presumably the
question is, what's אישתני למעליותא? ishtani l'maalyusa? The bread or the color?
The bread, the bread or the
color. I was always assuming that it meant the bread, but anyway,
if somehow this improves it, then כשרה. kshera. Yeah, the bread tastes
better. It could also mean that the color is now better because
you cooked it in this bread, but anyway,
כשרה, kshera, then it's valid. לגריעותא, l'griyusa, if it made it worse,
פסולה, psula, it's invalid. So that's how you do the test. וסימנך
v'simanach and the way you can remember this is, שינוי שקר שינוי
אמת, shinui sheker shinui emes, changing things for a lie and changing
things for telling the truth,
which רש"י—I Rashi didn't exactly get this רש"י—but Rashi רש"י says it
basically means
that if you're trying to lie, things—רש"י on פסולה psula he says
המשקר בדבריו ומשנה דיבורו לרעה, ha'mshaker bi'dvarav u'mshaneh diburo l'ra'ah, all know
that it's
bad. That when you're sort of
misrepresenting yourself for something bad, everybody knows it's bad. I don't get
it. שינוי אמת, shinui emes, המשנה דיבורו להוסיף או לקיים, ha'mshaneh diburo
l'hosif o l'kayem, all know that it's good.
I'm not sure what רש"י really means. Meaning, somehow if you're making
something sound worse than it is, then you're really dealing with something
bad, and if you're making something sound better than it is, you're
really dealing with something good. I really don't know the point here
of this idiomatic expression, but be that as it may, when it
makes it better it's good, when it makes it worse it's no
good. Anyway, so you see you have these ways of testing it.
מאי אין לה בדיקה נמי, mai ein la bdika nami, so what
does the ברייתא Braisa mean when it says that the תכלת techeiles
has no way of being tested? It doesn't mean you can't test
it. דקאמר אטעימה, d'ka'amar a'teima, it doesn't mean you can't test it,
it means that if you test it, you will invalidate it. Yes,
of course you can test it, but remember we said before you
have to take a little sample and test the sample because if
you test the whole thing then you're going to invalidate it. So
what it means it doesn't have testing means that you should not
be testing the whole vat. Okay, fine.
דקאמר אטעימה. d'ka'amar a'teima. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on and
says like this, where are we? Okay, fine.
מאי אין לה בדיקה נמי דקאמר אטעימה. mai ein la bdika nami
d'ka'amar a'teima. Okay, fine. מר ממשיכי Mar Mamshichi אייתי תכלתא בשני דרב
אחאי, aysei techelta bi'shnei d'Rav Achai, a certain person,
whatever, from ממשיכי Mamshichi took and brought תכלת techeiles. in the years
of רב אחאי. Rav Achai. בדקוה בדרב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה ואיפרח.
badkuha bi'd'Rav Yitzchak brei d'Rav Yehuda v'iprach. They ran the first test
about the urine and whatnot and the color
separated, ואיפרח חזותיה, v'iprach chazusei, and the color separated. ובדרב אדא ואישתני
למעליותא, u'vi'd'Rav Adda v'ishtani l'maalyusa, then they ran the second test with
the bread and it improved. So it failed one test and it
succeeded in the other.
סברו למיפסלה, savru l'mipsla, they thought to say it's invalid because as
long as it fails one test it's invalid.
אמר להו רב אחאי. amar lehu Rav Achai. אלא שמע מינה ela
shema mina so how are we going to explain what's going on
here? שמועה אהדדי איתמר shmu'ah ahadadi itmar so the two tests were
said in juxtaposition, meaning it wasn't like each test is sufficient because
here we see you can run the test and get different answers,
so it can't be that each test is an alternative. It must
be that somehow they work together. So let's take a look what
this means. איתמר היכא
דבדקנא itmar heicha debadkana they were said together. היכא דבדקנא ברב יצחק
בריה דרב יהודה לא אפרט חזותיה שפירא. heicha debadkana be-Rav Yitzchak brei
de-Rav Yehuda lo ephrat chazutei shapira. If you run test number one
and with the urine and whatnot and the color does not change,
then it's kosher. אפרט חזותיה, ephrat chazutei, if however the color has
changed, then בדקינן ליה ברב אדא בר חמא ארקאסא. badkinan lei be-Rav
Adda bar Chama arkasa. Then we do the second test with this
yeast, this sharp yeast. אשתני למעליותא כשרה לגריעותא פסולה ishtani le-ma'alyuta kshira
le-griyuta pesulah and the second test if it succeeds on the second
test then it would be kosher. So meaning these were not because
these were not parallel tests because then they would be yielding different
results. They were really like sequential tests. If the color does not
separate at all then you know for certain it's תכלת. techeiles If
the color does separate, well sometimes that also happens with תכלת techeiles,
as well, run this second test and this second test will tell
you. So in this case rather than saying it was invalid because
it succeeded in one and failed in the other and got contradictory
results, it actually said it was valid. It was conclusive and it
was valid because at least even though the second test failed, the
second one proved that in the end it really was good. Okay.
Anyways that's going on to our issue about testing for the קלא
אילן kala ilan but the also idea that טעימה פסולה te'imah pesulah
that because it because אין לה בדיקה meaning there's no way that
you're going to actually be able to test it before you know
with the that there's no way to test the original color because
that would invalidate the original color, therefore אין ניקחין אלא מן המומחה
ein nikchin ela min ha-mumcheh only buy from the מומחה mumche which
is again a little bit strange because even if טעימה te'imah invalidates
why don't you if you take it from a מומחה mumche, why
don't you take one piece of cloth that you're not going to
be using on your ציצית tzitzit and test that and then presumably
the rest are okay unless you can't be certain maybe the rest
of the strings were not colored with the same as the original
string? I mean even if it seems פסולה pesulah it's not exactly
clear why that only invalidates you know if you test the sample?
But for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara, is understanding no. Let me
just double check רש"י what he says. הגהות של טעימה שמפסידות כל
האורה, hagahot shel te'imah she-mafsi-dot kol ha-orah, yeah, doesn't help.
Yeah, רש"י doesn't really
explain that.
Okay,
let's keep on going. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So therefore if for some reason since you can't test the whole
vat and for some reason I don't know why you can't test
the sample which is not clear to me anyway you have to
buy your ציצית tzitzit from somebody who knows what they're doing. So
now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says like this. שלחו מתם
shalchu mi-tam they sent from there from Eretz Yisrael. שמועה אהדדי איתמר
shmu'ah ahadadi itmar it's true those two tests were said in juxtaposition,
they're not parallel but one follows the other. רב מני דייק וזבין
כחומרי מתניתין. Rav Mani daya'i ve-zavin ke-chumrei matnitin. רב מני Rav Mani
was very careful and he was only bought like the ברייתא braita
tells you that you're only have to you can only buy ציצית
tzitzit from a מומחה. mumche So he really followed that he was
careful about that. אמר ליה ההוא סבא הכי עביד קמאי דקמך ואצלח
עסקהון. amar lei hahu saba hachi avid kama'i de-kamach ve-atzlach askhon. That's
what your predecessors did and their business was very successful. So good
for you, that's what you should be doing, only buy מן המומחה.
All right. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. הלוקח תכלת מצוייצת מן השוק מישראל
הרי היא בחזקתה. ha-loke'ach techelet metzuyetzet min ha-shuk mi-Yisrael harei hi be-chezakatah.
If you buy a טלית tallit with ציצית tzitzit from a Jew,
so you can assume that the Jew used it as kosher and
therefore it is kosher and you can go on using it.
Here essentially we have a lower standard of מומחה mumche then because
if you can't buy except for מומחה mumche and here you're buying
it from someone in the שוק shuk we assume that most people
were straightforward.
Right but the whole point is that this is a personal use,
so if you're using it for yourself presumably it was checked and
so on, whereas if somebody's in the business then they're out to
make money and therefore there's greater concerns. So that seems to be
the difference although תוספות Tosafot does try to figure out exactly what
is the why how here did we have the you know what
was the point of the testing? Well let me first start by
quoting that question. So תוספות Tosafot asks a very simple question.
Well
let me just go ahead.
תוספות's Tosafot question is if you have to buy מן המומחה why
do we need to run the tests? Right? That's תוספות's Tosafot question.
Let me just try and go find how תוספות Tosafot. answers that.
Look at תוספות Tosafot מאי אין לה
בדיקה נמי דקאמר אטעימה Mai
ein la
bedikah nami dekamar ate'imah on the little תוספות Tosafos on מ"ג ע"א
mem-gimmel amud aleph he says ובדיקה דרב יצחק ודרב אדא אהני ללוקח
מן המומחה שיודע דטעימה פסולה אבל
לא ידע מקלא אילן.
u-vedika de-Rav Yitzchak u-de-Rav Adda ahani le-loke'ach min ha-mumcheh she-yode'a de-te'imah pesulah
aval lo
yada mi-kala ilan.
תוספות Tosafos says like this. Okay so the way תוספות Tosafos understands
and I'm sorry I was just sort of searching my data for
before תוספות Tosafos understands that when the גמרא Gemara: says why it's
only ניקחין מן המומחה nikchin min ha-mumcheh is not because you can't
run the test. You could run the test. Okay? Take out a
sample and run the test. Take out a sample of even the
ציצית tzitzis strings that they sold you. וניקח מן המומחה v'nikach min
hamumche means that because if the person making it did not know
the הלכות halachos of טעימה, te'ima, he would have invalidated the whole
vat.
Now you've got a problem because even if it's real תכלת, techeiles,
right, how do you know that the guy didn't invalidate the whole
vat by doing the טעימה? te'ima? That's how תוספות Tosafos thinks that
אין בו בדיקה. ein bo bedika. Not you can't test. You will
know if it's קלא אילן kala ilan, or not. But you don't
know that the guy didn't invalidate everything. So that's how תוספות Tosafos
says that's the balance. You do your טעימה te'ima test and you're
going to... and that's the purpose of this test. You're going to
know if it's קלא אילן kala ilan, or not. Good, it's not
קלא אילן, kala ilan it's תכלת. techeiles But you need to also
buy it from somebody who knows the הלכות halachos because he might
have inadvertently used קלא אילן, kala ilan. okay, and if you don't
assume he's deceiving, so that's why you run your test. But you
have to know that he doesn't make the mistake of doing the
טעימה te'ima that will invalidate. So that's how תוספות Tosafos strikes the
balance between these two... So מומחה is going to be certain not
to do the טעימה te'ima in a way that doesn't invalidate, and
but he might have been duped in terms of the קלא אילן
kalla ilan or whatever, so you run your own test.
Maybe the מומחה, why do you assume that the מומחה also, he
knows
the הלכות halachot of טעימה te'ima also knows this test? I don't
know, it doesn't say that. The מומחה can run this test if
he bought his תכלת techeilet from some supplier, then he can run
this test as well. Right, we could also say... Okay, anyway that's
how תוספות strikes that balance. So then now we get back to
this דעת da'as thing about... the רמב"ם Rambam has a different explanation
if I can find it one second. I remember what the רמב"ם
Rambam says. רמב"ם says: התכלת אינן ניקחת אלא מן המומחה
חושש
שמא
לא
נטפל
לשמה, Ha'techeiles einan nilkachas ella min hamumche choshesh shema lo nitpal
lishmah,
which is sort of like the תוספות. The לשמה issue is similar
to the טעימה te'ima issue that he would have invalidated. ואף על
פי שניקחת מן המומחה אם נבדקה ונודע שנטפלה באחד מן הטיבונים המשחירים
שאינם עומדים פסולה כיצד בודק. V'af al pi she'nilkachas min hamumche im
nivdeka v'noda she'nitpela be'achad min hativonim hamashchirim she'einom omdim psula keitzad bodek.
So right, in the רמב"ם it sounds like you don't have to
run the test. It's like if you found out that you were
duped, then obviously it becomes invalid. But anyway, תוספות and the רמב"ם
are at least for saying that the מומחה is to know that
he knows לשמה and is not going to do the טעימה te'ima
that's going to invalidate, and then this is a test you can
run to make sure it's real תכלת. Now getting back to our
גמרא, Gemara, our גמרא Gemara, says let's take a look: תנו רבנן
הלוקח טלית מצויצת מן השוק מישראל הרי היא בחזקת כשרה. Tanu rabbanan
halokeach tallis metzuyetzes min hashuk mi'Yisrael harei hi bechezkat kashra. So if
you buy it from a Jew, you're not buying it from the
seller or the manufacturer, you're buying it from a Jew, so we
assume that he did what he needed to do to check that
it was good and therefore you can just buy it and assume
that it's כשר. kasher, מן העובד
כוכבים, Min ha'oved kochavim, if you're buying
it from a non-Jew, however, מן התגר כשרה מן ההדיוט
פסולה.
min hatagar kashra
min
hahediyot psula.
If you're buying it from a merchant it's כשר, kasher from a
layperson it's invalid. Why is it כשר kasher? from a merchant? So
the גמרא Gemara says let's take a look at the גמרא: Gemara
מן ההדיוט פסולה ואף על פי שאמרו אין אדם רשאי למכור טלית
מצויצת לעובד כוכבים עד שיתיר ציציותיה. min hahediyot psula v'af al pi
she'amru ein adam rashai limkor tallis metzuyetzes l'oved kochavim ad she'yattir tzitzitoseha.
Even though they said that a person is not allowed to sell
a טלית tallis with ציצית tzitzis to a non-Jew until you undo
the strings... what is the reason? We're going to say in a
minute, because then it'll allow them to appear like a Jew. Nevertheless,
assuming that a person... sometimes it did happen that people would sell
their טליתות tallisos to a non-Jew, and therefore you can buy it
from a non-Jew. So what you are buying from a non-Jew here
is not a newly manufactured טלית, tallis, right? טלית מצויצת, Tallis metzuyetzes,
again, remember in our mindset ציצית tzitzis is classically the garment with
the strings. In the גמרא, Gemara, what's ציצית? tzitzis? ציצית Tzitzis are
the strings themselves and you would just buy the בגד. beged. So
if you're buying a טלית מצויצת, tallis metzuyetzes, you're not going to
the marketplace and saying oh I need to buy some ציצית. tzitzis.
Right, you're saying oh look at that lovely garment there, I'd like
to buy it. It happens to be that there are ציצית tzitzis
on it. Can I assume that those ציצית tzitzis were placed on
correctly or not? That's טלית מצויצת. tallis metzuyetzes. Your interest is in
buying the garment, your interest is not in I have to buy
a בגד ציצית beged tzitzis because that was not the case in
the גמרא, Gemara that's not the מצוה. mitzvah. So what is it?
So I'm probably going to tell you, so if you're buying it
from a Jew, you assume the Jew did his מצוה mitzvah correctly.
If you're buying it from a non-Jew, so it's not like buying
the תכלת from the non-Jew or buying the strings from a non-Jew.
Obviously
there we would have concerns about לשמה and does he know the
הלכה halacha and is it קלא אילן. Here, he presumably bought this
as used clothes from a Jew and is now reselling it at
to other Jews. So it just happens to be a gorgeous Armani
suit that he bought up and now he's selling it on eBay
and happens to be that the ציצית tzitzis were already put on
by his previous purchaser. Can you assume that they're כשר? kasher So
presumably take a look, of course! I mean who had it before
him? It has to have been another Jew. So therefore I should
be able to assume it's okay. So that's why מן התגר min
hatagar it's כשרה, kashra, because the תגר tagar is presumably just reselling
it, but he's in the business, he buys stuff wholesale. But he
resells it, so the stuff he has at this instance is because
it's used for ציצית, tzitzis, so you're okay.
However, if it's a manufacturer, no, then you'd have to be concerned
about קלא אילן and לשמה and תעשה ולא מן העשוי, taaseh v'lo
min ha-asuy, all that stuff. But he's just a reseller. Okay, however,
if it's the layperson, so then the layperson, no. You figure a
layperson maybe is doing it דווקא davka as a way to make
money. Oh, I've got this one garment I want to sell it,
you know, it's a, you know, and therefore I'll put ציצית tzitzis
on it so Jews will want to buy it more. Okay, so
if it's my business, I'm not going to endanger my business, and
we assume that this is what I do anyway, I buy this
stuff up. If it's the layperson, we assume that he's duping me.
Okay, now, and even though you're not allowed, even though, why isn't
it a problem? How did this, even if this guy's the reseller,
how did he buy it from Jews? Aren't Jews not allowed to
sell their garments to non-Jews until they remove the ציצית? tzitzis? Nevertheless,
we assume that sometimes it happens that they would, and therefore we
will assume that these are כשר if
they're bought by a reseller. והלכתא כוותיה. v'hilcheta kevaseih. No, that makes
it okay. Exactly, right, interesting presumption. Exactly, exactly. Right, normally wouldn't violate
this. What?
Right, and if it was only very rare, then we would assume
that, you know, maybe he's just like the layperson and we have
to be afraid that he's pulling one over on us. Exactly. Now,
מאי טעמא, mai taama, what is the reason? Again, it does though
reflect this reality about how ציצית, tzitzis, you know, we totally focus
on a garment with ציצית tzitzis as a מצוה mitzvah garment. But
if you're basically focusing on this garment as, you know, this is
just my shirt, this is just my cloak, oh yeah, I had
to put on these fringes because that's what הלכה halacha requires. It
doesn't mean that when you decide to sell your old suit, you're
going to very much focus on your need to remove your ציצית,
tzitzis, because you're not relating to them as a מצוה mitzvah garment,
you're relating to them as your suit. You know, okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאי טעמא, mai taama, now why
are you not allowed to sell your garment with ציצית tzitzis on
it to a non-Jew? הכא תרגמו משום זונה. hacha targumu mishum zona.
Here they explain it because of a זונה, zona, okay. I'll explain
that in a minute. ורב יהודה אמר שמא יתלווה עמו בדרך. v'Rav
Yehuda amar shema yitlaweh imo baderech. And רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said,
maybe the non-Jew will accompany you on the road. You know, you'll
think he's Jewish and therefore you'll be willing to, you know, go
with him into some dark alley, ויהרגנו, v'yahargenu, and he will kill
him.
So now we're like back into עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, the concern
is always either about the non-Jew's, either about murder or about עריות.
arayos. The עריות arayos concern is not exactly clear. רש״י Rashi says
that it's the non-Jew will maybe give this garment to a, to
a prostitute, and then the prostitute will have this garment, so people
will think the Jew was sleeping with her, which is about to
evoke the גמרא Gemara we're going to have, that famous אגדתא aggadata
about the man and his ציצית tzitzis with the prostitute. So somehow,
people, it will look like a Jew is consorting with a prostitute,
or either because he'll be wearing this garment when he goes to
the prostitute, or he'll give it to the prostitute, whatever. And the
other one is the more obvious concern, that he'll be able to
appear as a Jew, and therefore you'll get in trouble by trusting
him and going into a dark alley with him. I should say
what's important about all of this is, and this gets into the
deeper issue of ציצית tzitzis which we'll discuss very briefly, is it
does point to how central clothing is in terms of identity, and
in terms of saying, you know, marking you for who you are,
Jewish or not Jewish, and so on, which is like, you know,
major, so certainly by ציצית, tzitzis, the major thing, you know, וראו
כל עמי הארץ, v'rau kol amei ha-aretz, that's תפילין. But anyway,
well, by תפילין you have a parallel וראו כל עמי הארץ כי
שם ה׳ נקרא עליך. v'rau kol amei ha-aretz ki shem Hashem nikra
alecha. By ציצית tzitzis normally it's like you look at the ציצית
tzitzis וזכרתם, v'zachartem, it's your
subjective remembering. But let's face it, anybody that's wearing ציצית, tzitzis, you
know, in a way that's visible to people, very clearly marks that
person as Jewish. And so this גמרא, Gemara I think, is, you
know, talking about it from a very practical concern, but in terms
of also a sense of like the טעמי המצוות taamei ha-mitzvos and
having that clear Jewish identity is certainly something that's there as well.
So the prostitute is sort of like multi-laws a community, it's not
for a particular person, and that's what we're concerned about.
Right, yeah, that's exactly it.
Okay. Plus first, the first view of the prostitute,
yeah, that's more interesting, right?
Yeah, from prostitute, that alright, so she, her, her Jewish customers, right,
so
today got non-Jewish
customers, kind of like the, the one who's suspect about תכלת, right?
You, you're, it, I understand that he might sell, he might not
take the ציצית tzitzis off when he sells the garment, but he's
going to do the תכלת, right?
Wait, he's not going to take the ציצית tzitzis off when you
buy it directly from him. But that's not the same person.
No, it's not,
but it's the same, right, that people will, right, people won't do
this but they will do that. Right, exactly. Good point. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's continue. תנו רבנן. Rabbanan Okay,
I'm sorry, I skipped.
Now we get into, I'm very disappointed that רבקה's Rivka not here,
because she would certainly have what to say about the גמרות Gemoras
we're going to be doing next. Okay, so let's take a look.
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, back to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה
רמי תכלתא לפרזומא. Rav Yehuda rami techeilsa l'parzuma.
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda put תכלת in the פרזומא, parzuma, which is
some type of a cloak.
Right, the פרזומא parzuma דאינשי ביתיה d'inshei beiseih of the people of
his house. Now, the people of his house is a euphemism. House
means wife. So אינשי ביתיה inshei beiseih means basically his wife or
the women of, and he notes it says אינשי?
inshei? Yeah. Instead of נשי? neshei? Yeah.
The house is the women's area, so the people of his house
are his wife. people of the house are the women. Okay, specifically
his wife, but the women of the house. He put, he put
ציצית tzitzit on the garments of his wife and daughters. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara, says
ומברך כל צפרא להתעטף בציצית umivarech kol tzafra lihit'atef betzitzit and every
morning he made the ברכה beracha להתעטף
בציצית.
lihit'atef
betzitzit. They borrowed her? No, no, no, on his own garment. Okay,
two הלכות of ציצית. tzitzit. When he put on his ציצית tzitzit
he said להתעטף בציצית lihit'atef betzitzit and he put ציצית tzitzit on
his wife's garment. So now we're going to, now we're going to
take this apart. מדרמי, mi-darmi, since he put the ציצית tzitzit on
of his wife's garment, קסבר מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא היא. kasavar mitzvat
asei shehazman grama hi. So it's a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvat
asei shehazman grama because the question is, is night excluded from ציצית?
tzitzit? As you might have discussed, this came up right two days
ago, right over יום טוב. Yom Tov. So as you might have
discussed, there's a question in the פוסקים, Poskim, what does it mean
night is exempt? Does it mean nighttime I don't have to wear
ציצית? tzitzit? Or does it mean a garment that is made for
night wear like pajamas, I don't have to have ציצית? tzitzit? That
might be dependent on the debate of whether ציצית tzitzit is a
חובת גברא chovat gavra or a חובת מנא? chovat mana? But nevertheless,
the גמרא Gemara understands that if night is exempt, even if it's
about night garments being exempt, it means הזמן גרמא hazman grama that
time limits the obligation and therefore women are exempt. But there was
a debate whether night is exempt or not. So if night is
not exempt, so therefore you're always obligated in ציצית tzitzit and therefore
women would be חייב. chayav. So here we see that ציצית, tzitzit,
he put it on on the garments of his wife, we see
he holds מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא הוא, mitzvat asei she-lo hazman
grama hu, that it's not limiting. So if that's true, אמאי מברך
כל צפרא וצפרא, amai mevarech kol tzafra vetzafra, why does he make
a ברכה beracha every morning? He's always doing the same מצוה, mitzvah,
right? It's consistently one מצוה. mitzvah. There's no time period where he
is not commanded, so it should only be one ברכה beracha like
his entire life. Now one ברכה beracha your entire life sounds a
little bit bizarre. Some of the אחרונים, Achronim, I think the קרן
אורה Keren Ora wants to say this a little more sharply. Well
let me just say, what's the גמרא Gemara saying? Since if the
מצוה mitzvah applies throughout the night, right? So therefore he should not
have, he should only have to make his ברכה beracha once, not
it applies when you wear it. First of all, didn't he take
it off at night? Yes.
So if he took it off and fell asleep, isn't that הפסק?
hefsek? Why does the גמרא Gemara assume that it would be consistent?
That's question number one. Question number two is, so what do you
want to say, somebody makes a ברכה beracha ציצית tzitzit once your
entire life? So the way that this is sharpened and redefined, I
forget where it says this, I think it might be the קרן
אורה, Keren Ora, he says no, here's the story. If he holds
that
לילה זמן ציצית, laila zman tzitzit, so it's a מצות עשה שלא
הזמן גרמא. mitzvat asei she-lo hazman grama. So you could say that
that means that fundamentally night is... I'm trying to remember who said,
I might be saying this not correctly, but it's something like this.
It could mean that fundamentally night is included in the מצוה, mitzvah,
or it could mean that he understands that the whole issue of
night is only about the בגד, beged, בגד לילה, beged laila, בגד
יום. beged yom. And therefore it doesn't really make it אין הזמן
גרמא. ein hazman grama. And if you emphasize that the whole מצוה
mitzvah is about the בגד, beged, therefore then the מצוה mitzvah is
really not when you wear it, the מצוה mitzvah is when you
put the ציצית tzitzit on, like we learned before. So therefore you're
not going to make it every morning when you come to wake
up. Okay, that's a little bit, a little ingenious, I don't think
that's the simple פשט pshat of the גמרא, Gemara because the גמרא
Gemara sounds like he basically holds completely that לילה זמן ציצית. laila
zman tzitzit. Okay, so anyway that's the גמרא's Gemara question. If לילה
זמן ציצית, laila zman tzitzit, why do you make it every morning?
A little strange question, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, כרבי, ki-Rebbi,
he's going like רבי. Rebbi. דתניא תפילין
כל זמן שמניחן מברך עליהן דברי רבי. detanya tefillin kol zman shemenichan
mevarech aleihen divrei Rebbi.
Every time you put them on you make a ברכה, beracha, that's
what רבי Rebbi says,
so presumably even if you take them off and put them on
the same time during the day. So it doesn't matter that it's
all one consistent time period, if you took it off and put
it back on again you make another ברכה. beracha.
ובכל זאת לילה זמן, u-v'chol zot laila zman, it is a מצוה,
mitzvah, a total מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvat asei shehazman grama because
you don't...
Yeah, but presumably רבי Rebbi means even if it's during the time
period of continuous חיוב. chiyuv. Even if I took it off at
9:00 AM and I put it on at 2:00 PM, I make
another ברכה. beracha. So if I make another ברכה beracha two times
during the day, even though there's been a continuous חיוב, chiyuv, I'm
going to make another ברכה beracha when I put ציצית tzitzit on
the next morning even though there's a continuous חיוב, chiyuv, right? Which
is what we normally assume. The fact that, in order to be
מחייב mechayev me a new ברכה, beracha, it's enough to have any
factor to create a הפסק. hefsek. Either it becomes a period where
I'm not obligated to wear it like לילה, laila, or let's say
I go to the bathroom or some place I can't wear it,
or there was just actually a subjective הפסק, hefsek, I took it
off and I didn't plan on putting it back on, I put
it back on later, that's fine, who cares that it's a continuous...
who cares, it's a continuous זמן, zman, you take it off and
you put it back on, you make another ברכה. beracha. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true,
כל שעתא נמי, kol sha'ata nami, so he should make it every...
so he should make it every time he puts it back on.
Why does he just make it in the morning? Make it every
time he puts it back on. So he didn't. So the גמרא
Gemara says רב יהודה איניש צניעא הוא, Rav Yehuda inish tznia hu,
he was a very private man, a very, you know, careful about
his modesty. ולא שרי ליה לגלימיה כולי יומא, v'lo sharei lei l'glimei
kulei yoma, he would never take his clothes off. Maybe the גמרא
Gemara assumed that, you know, people generally would go to the bathhouse
or something. So anyway it says no, once he wore his garment
in the morning he would not take it off the whole day
until the nighttime and therefore אי נמי, ei nami, when it says
every morning it doesn't mean every morning, what it really means is
every time he would put on his garment, just for him that
was once in the day.
Okay, ומאי שנא מצפרא, u-mai shna mitzafra, so why do we say
the morning? כי משני מצופאי לכסות יומא, ki mishanei mitzufei lichsut yoma,
because that's when he's going to get put on his night... his
day clothes. When he puts on his day clothes he makes a...
a ברכה. bracha. Okay so of course if he holds that לילה
לאו זמן תפילין laila lav zman tfillin he also should make a
ברכה bracha when he puts on his night clothes if they require
ציצית tzitzis excuse me אם זמן ציצית im zman tzitzis he should
put on a ברכה bracha when he makes his night clothes because
he holds that לילה זמן ציצית laila zman tzitzis and the answer
might be אינה הכי נמי. ina hachi nami. So until now what
we said is very simple: he holds that לילה laila is זמן
ציצית zman tzitzis that women are obligated, he makes a ברכה bracha
every time he puts on his garment anew even though it's a
continuous period that does not mean you don't make a new ברכה
bracha when you put on a garment anew you are going to
make
a and are the women going to make a ברכה bracha when
they
yeah the women presumably would also though that's debated that's not clear
that's between אשכנזים Ashkenazim and no that would if he holds women
are really חייב chayav the whole debate about women make a ברכה
bracha is when they're פטור patur and they do it anyway but
he holds they're חייב chayav then the women in his house his
wife and his daughters yes would have to make a ברכה. bracha.
Okay so here you have the idea about making it in the
morning but להלכה l'halacha we don't limit it to the morning you
know להלכה l'halacha we basically say that you do it what do
you call it that you do it every time you if you
take off your ציצית tzitzit and you really have a סילוק דעת
shiluk da'at not like you're planning on putting them right on again
you really are מסיח דעת mesiach da'at then you put them on
again then you actually would make another ברכה. bracha. I should say
though by the way very against the גמרא Gemara but in line
with what we were saying before the idea of making it once
in the morning which for the גמרא Gemara felt was very specific
right the גמרא Gemara is really resisting the idea that it doesn't
mean once in the morning it really means every time he gets
dressed okay he really thought there was something דוקא davka about doing
it once in the morning and to me if you ask what
ברכה bracha do we make every day that is really a little
ambiguous whether it's a ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzva or not and we
do it every morning this is directly parallel to the
ברכת התורה birchas haTorah right ברכת התורה birchas haTorah there's a whole
question that תוספות asks why do we make it once in the
day and we're done why don't we make it every time we're
מפסיק mafsik you know and so on and so this is what
we're not really מפסיק mafsik we're always planning on getting back to
it but anyway part of the reason we do ברכת התורה birchas
haTorah just once in the morning is it's ברכת התורה birchas haTorah
is not so much a ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzva it's also a
ברכת השבח birchas hashevach right אשר בחר בנו ונתן לנו asher bachar
banu v'nasan lanu so from that perspective you make it once in
the you make it on the daily basis that's about about the
ברכת התורה birchas haTorah so one wonders again if he's saying that
לילה laila is זמן ציצית zman tzitzis and if connected to that
is a de-emphasis on the חובת גברא chovas gavra more on the
חובת מנא chovas mana right and therefore it's not so much about
whether it's daytime or nighttime it's about the garment having it and
always having them on the garments then it's also possible to understand
you know the אחרונים achronim already ask this question if you're פוסק
paskening that לילה laila is זמן ציצית zman tzitzis is if it's
חובת מנא chovas mana do you make a ברכה bracha of להתעטף
בציצית l'hitatef b'tzitzit when you put it on if the מצוה mitzvah
is having them on the garment not להתעטף l'hitatef and the תוספתא
Tosefta says you do make that ברכה bracha and presumably nobody argues
on that תוספתא. Tosefta. So the answer might be yes but if
you're making it it's more of a ברכת השבח birchas hashevach and
less of a ברכת המצוה. birchas hamitzva. The מצוה mitzvah was when
I put the ציצית tzitzis on but now when I'm encountering the
מצוה mitzvah you know sort of like the ברכת התורה אשר קדשנו
birchas haTorah asher kideshanu could be more of a שבח shevach for
having been given the תורה Torah, rather than a limited ברכת המצוה
birchas hamitzva and that would then explain why you would make it
every morning you would make it in the context of a type
of a ברכת השבח birchas hashevach not in the context of I'm
sorry so wait do you say the reason you say להתעטף l'hitatef
totally against the גמרא Gemara but I'm saying you have להתעטף בציצית
l'hitatef b'tzitzit that everybody presumably says you make what about the person
that says it's a חובת מנא chovas mana why are you making
להתעטף בציצית l'hitatef b'tzitzit right so some try to sort of say
well it's not totally חובת מנא חובת מנא chovas mana chovas mana
is get actualized and experienced when you wind up wearing it but
I'm saying is well maybe according to him the להתעטף l'hitatef ברכה
bracha in the morning would be more of a ברכת השבח birchas
hashevach you know that you're now encountering ציצית tzitzis so there's a
שבח shevach to that not necessarily ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzva to that
and that would fit in with the idea of מברך כל צפרא.
mevarech kol tzafra.
Why only certain מצות mitzvos have this ברכת השבח? birchas hashevach?
What? Yeah well that's a good question.
That's a good question.
Yeah I'd have to I'll get back to you on that. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says anyway it's not the way the
גמרא Gemara is understanding the גמרא Gemara is understanding that it was
basically because it was the מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah it's just there
was a הפסק hefsek he went to sleep he put on new
clothes he makes a new ברכה. bracha. Okay. Now תנו רבנן. Now
we're going to focus a little bit on the women issue which
we talked about before. תנו רבנן הכל חייבין בציצית. tanu rabbanan hakol
chayavin b'tzitzis. Everybody is חייב chayav in ציצית. tzitzis. כהנים לויים וישראלים
kohanim leviyim v'yisraelim okay which like is a little bit obvious גרים
נשים ועבדים gerim nashim v'avadim and converts women and slaves. Converts is
interesting because normally since when are converts ever treated different? Women and
slaves is even if it's a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה mitzvas asei
shehazman grama it's not a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה mitzvas asei shehazman
grama this is the opinion that לילה laila is זמן ציצית. zman
tzitzis.
What about קטנים? ktanim?
So doesn't it that's only going to be for חינוך. chinuch. רבי
שמעון פוטר בנשים מפני שמצות עשה שהזמן גרמה הוא rabbi shimon poter
banashim mipnei shemitzvas asei shehazman grama hu and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says no women are exempt because it's a time-bound positive commandment. So
presumably the חכמים chachamim say לילה laila is זמן ציצית zman tzitzis
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's not and any מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמה נשים פטורות mitzvas asei shehazman grama nashim pturos and anything
that is
a time-bound women are exempt.
So now let's look at this. אמר מר הכל חייבין בציצית כהנים
לויים וישראלים. amar mar hakol chayavin b'tzitzis kohanim leviyim v'yisraelim. גמרא Gemara
says פשיטא obviously דאי כהנים לויים וישראלים פטירי de'ee kohanim leviyim v'yisraelim
ptirei if כהנים לויים kohanim leviyim and ישראלים yisraelim are exempt מאן
מחייב man michayev who do you want to be חייב? chayav? Of
course who else is חייב? chayav? Of course you know the first
thing about anything is that you know is that the adult men
are חייב chayav and no distinction כהן לוי kohen levi or so
what's the חידוש chiddush of that whole line? So rather than saying
that it was a throwaway here's what the גמרא Gemara says: כהנים
איצטריכא ליה kohanim itzterichlei no you need to tell me by the
כהנים. kohanim. סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach amina I might have thought
כהן כתיב לא תלבש שעטנז kohen ksiv lo tilbash shaatnez צמר ופשתן
יחדיו tzemer ufishtan yachdav don't wear שעטנז shaatnez wool and linen together
גדילים תעשה לך gedelim ta'aseh lach make fringes for yourself. make for
yourself ציצית, tzitzis, מאן דלא אשתרי כלאים לגביה Man d'lo ishtari kilayim
legabei בלבישה הוא דמיחייב בציצית. balivishah hu demichayev b'tzitzis. Somebody who never
has an exemption of כלאים, kilayim, that's the person that's חייב chayiv
in ציצית, tzitzis, meaning a normal lay person. הני כהנים בכהנים, Hani
Kohanim baKohanim, הוי אשתרי כלאים לגבייהו, hovi ishtari kilayim legavaihu, since כלאים
kilayim is waived for them when it comes to some of the
בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehunah, so לא ליחייבו, lo litchayevu, they're
not included. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan that they are. Okay, that
the, okay, well, whatever. Anyway, I might have thought that the גדילים
תעשה לך Gedilim taaseh lach is only for people that are in
the category of לא תלבש שעטנז. lo silbash shaatnez. Now it's a
bizarre הוה אמינא. hava amina. It's easier to say the גמרא's Gemara
line is a throwaway, but I did want to say something about
this, which I think I mentioned yesterday, which is this echo in
the גמרא Gemara, or this subtext in the גמרא Gemara, about comparing
ציצית tzitzis to בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. Maybe I'm listening into it
a little too hard and maybe it's not really there. But anyway
be that as it may, the גמרא Gemara already said by תפילין
that תפילין is like the ציץ. tzitz. Well, you know, by the
ציצית, tzitzis, there's I think a whole more of a comparison to
an implicit comparison to the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. On the one
hand you have this הוה אמינא hava amina right now for כהן,
Kohen, though the גמרא Gemara. framed it as כלאים, kilayim, but a
כהן Kohen normally wears כלאים, kilayim, which means that we're thinking about
the כהן Kohen in the context of the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah.
So that type of person doesn't need ציצית. tzitzis. Who needs ציצית?
tzitzis? The ישראל Yisrael that doesn't normally in that category of wearing
כלאים. kilayim. In a way, therefore, the ציצית tzitzis becomes a type
of a תחליף tachlif for בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. It actually occurred
to me that the גמרא, Gemara so A, there's this line which
is, it might be a throwaway but it's interesting. B, there's the
point תוספות makes, which I mentioned to you yesterday, that even if
you're not doing the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית, tzitzis, it's the like
it's nighttime or women or whatever, if the בגד beged has ציצית
tzitzis that were made through שעטנז, shaatnez, right, wool strings in a
linen garment or whatever, the שעטנז shaatnez comes as a result of
the ציצית, tzitzis, it's totally excluded from laws of כלאים, kilayim, and
תוספות says like בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. And therefore even if it
was done at night or it was done not in the context
of a מצוה, mitzvah, a woman or whatever, the בגד beged is
like בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah and it's excluded categorically as a בגד,
beged, a בגד beged with כלאים. kilayim. And that's also this גמרא,
Gemara the idea of a בגד beged with שעטנז. shaatnez. On the
one hand it's the worst thing, it's an עבירה aveira of שעטנז,
shaatnez, and on the other hand it evokes בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehunah,
because בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah had שעטנז. shaatnez. So the גמרא Gemara,
is set to say, 'Ah, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, that's the point.
If you have בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah you don't have ציצית, tzitzis,
if you have ציצית tzitzis you don't have, you know, בגדי כהונה,
bigdei kehunah, whatever.' So that's this גמרא. Gemara. Maybe it doesn't apply
to כהנים. Kohanim. And תוספות therefore said if you have a בגד
beged with שעטנז, shaatnez, maybe it's like בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah and
it's totally excluded, and therefore even if you're not doing the מצוה.
mitzvah.
And therefore it becomes almost the irony, since we allow שעטנז shaatnez
is almost the only model we have for that is בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehunah. So then we conceive of the ציצית tzitzis as a
type of a בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. And I did want to
say within that context, which is a beautiful idea then, then you
have the idea that, okay, we don't have a מקדש Mikdash anymore,
right, and what, if we don't have a מקדש, Mikdash, but what
do we have? We wear תפילין, the ציץ, tzitz, we wear ציצית,
tzitzis, which is our בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. And actually when we
now have that קדושה kedusha not limited to one little place in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and one little group of people, the
כהנים, Kohanim, we now have that קדושה, kedusha, you know, everywhere. We
have, we you know as a type of a בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehunah, a type of a ציצית tzitzis etc. It evokes the ראש
Rosh who says the reason we do נטילת ידים netilas yadayim in
the morning is a type of a, you know, like the כהנים
Kohanim do the נטילת ידים netilas yadayim before entering into the מקדש,
Mikdash, which sanctifies the entire world, not just the מקדש. Mikdash. So
within that line I've been thinking that, you know, the גמרא Gemara
has two types of garments that it's very,
what's the word, like, obsessed
with, focused on,
hyper-focused, סדין בציצית sadin b'tzitzis and טלית שכולה תכלת. tallis shekulah techeles.
So you know טלית שכולה תכלת tallis shekulah techeles makes us think
about קורח. Korach. But, you know, I thought it bothered me, what
is this כולה? kulah? Why not just say טלית של תכלת? tallis
shel techeles? All the questions it had about it, you know, what's
the כולה kulah and we have הדין תכלת. hadin techeles. Ah, so...
but yeah, because where do we, if you think about it, the
two בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah that are basically the major garments are
the כתונת kesones and the מעיל. me'il. The כתונת kesones is סדין
sadin and the מעיל me'il is כולה תכלת. kulah techeles. So the
two major בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehunah, I mean meaning like basic garments,
not your underwear and your hat and your belt, but the basic
garments are the סדין sadin and the כולה תכלת. kulah techeles. So
I'm wondering if that's really, the גמרא Gemara. is sort of, you
know, that's a subtext being going on.
And you know one interesting point, if you don't mind me making
it, that according to the רמב"ם, I forget which one it was,
didn't he say that the מעיל me'il or one of them was
basically like a
טלית tallis with a hole in it but it still didn't require
ציצית? tzitzis? So then based on that, קל וחומר kal v'chomer it
should require.
No, that's beautiful then, this גמרא, Gemara right, the בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehunah, that's exactly this גמרא. Gemara The כהנים, Kohanim, they don't need
their ציצית, tzitzis, they've got their בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. You know,
so the כהנים... Kohanim... but we who don't have בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehunah, we need our ציצית tzitzis to make it into בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehunah. Okay, so now anyway let's keep on going. So that
was an interesting
הוה אמינא. hava amina. Okay. נהי דאישתרי בעידן עבודה, Nehi d'ishtari b'idan
avodah, it's true that they are exempt from it when they're doing
their עבודה. avodah. בלא עידן עבודה לא אישתרי, B'lo idan avodah lo
ishtari, when they're not doing their עבודה avodah they're not exempt. They're
not allowed to wear their בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehunah, I mean there's
תוספות has a whole range of explanations what this means, but פשט
pshat it means that even they're not allowed to wear their בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehunah with כלאים kilayim when they're not doing their עבודה.
avodah. And therefore they're not really fully exempt from כלאים, kilayim, and
therefore that cannot the פסוק pasuk is not meaning to limit, exclude
כהנים Kohanim from the מצוה. mitzvah. ורבי שמעון פוטר, V'Rabbi Shimon poter,
Rabbi Shimon exempts בנשים. benashim. Wait, why are we mentioning בנשים binashim
though?
Are there, they never had a
היתר heter for כלאים.
kilayim. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says why do we need, yeah, okay.
רבי שמעון פוטר בנשים, Rabbi Shimon poter binashim, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
exempts by women. מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mah taama d'Rabbi Shimon? דתניא,
D'tanya, וראיתם אתו, u're'isem oso, פרט לכסות לילה. prat l'khsuso layla. You
shall see it, which excludes a garment of night. אתה אומר פרט
לכסות לילה, Atah omer prat l'khsuso layla, או אינו אלא פרט לכסות
סומא? o eino ela prat l'khsuso suma? Maybe it's excluding a blind
person who can't see it? כשהוא אומר Keshehu omer אשר תכסה בה,
asher t'khasse bah, you shall make them on the garment you wear,
הרי כסות סומא אמור. Harei khsuso suma amur. It speaks about even
a blind person because that's a ריבוי. ribui. So who's it including?
It's including even a blind person who can't see it. הא מה
אני מקיים וראיתם אתו? Ha mah ani mekayem u're'isem oso? So why
does the Torah emphasize you have to see it if not to
exclude a blind person? פרט לכסות לילה, Prat l'khsuso layla, to exclude
garments of night that they're not obligated in ציצית. tzitzis. ומה ראית
לרבות כסות סומא ולהוציא כסות לילה? u'mah ra'isa l'rabos khsuso suma u'lehotzi
khsuso layla? What if you had to choose between two, right? One
is inclusive and the other is limiting. Why say we're going to
include the garment of a blind person and exclude night garments? מרבה
אני כסות סומא Marbe ani khsuso suma שישנה בראיה אצל אחרים. sheyeshnah
b're'iyah etzel acherim. I include the garment of blind people because other
people see them, so they are fit to be seen. ומוציא אני
כסות לילה u'motzi ani khsuso layla שאינה בראיה אצל אחרים she'einah b're'iyah
etzel acherim are not seen to be seen. So רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says yeah, וראיתם אתו u're'isem oso exclude garments that are not
fit to be seen or that are not normally seen, which are
night garments. Those are not obligated and therefore it's a זמן גרמא.
zman grama. ורבנן, V'Rabanan, what do the Rabbis say? האי אשר תכסה
בה מאי עבדי ליה? Hai asher t'khasse bah mai avdi lei? Presumably
they don't exclude night garments or סומא suma garments. So since they
don't read the פסוק passuk of וראיתם אתו u're'isem oso
to tell me they have to be seeable. So if they don't
have to be seeable and both a garments of a blind person
and night garments are obligated, what do they do with the ריבוי
ribui of אשר תכסה בה? asher t'khasse bah? What do they need
it for? The גמרא Gemara says מבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibayei lei l'khid'tanya,
what we learned in the ברייתא, braisa, ארבע כנפות כסותך, arba kanfos
k'suskha, on the four corners of your garment, ארבע ולא שלש, arba
v'lo shalosh, only if you have four corners, not three. אתה אומר
ארבע ולא שלש, Atah omer arba v'lo shalosh, או אינו אלא ארבע
ולא חמש? o eino ela arba v'lo chamesh? Maybe even if I
have five corners, I don't have to put on ציצית? tzitzis? כשהוא
אומר Keshehu omer אשר תכסה בה, asher t'khasse bah, it has an
extra word that you cover yourself with, which includes even more
garments. הרי בעלת חמש אמור. Harei ba'alas chamesh amur. That tells you
a five-cornered garment you do put ציצית tzitzis
in every corner.
No, well, that was a debate earlier, we פסקן pasken on four
corners. Okay.
ומה אני מקיים על ארבע? u'mah ani mekayem al arba? So why
does the
Torah say on your four corners if even a five-cornered garment is
חייב? chayav? ארבע ולא שלש Arba v'lo shalosh to exclude three. ומה
ראית לרבות בעלת חמש ולהוציא בעלת שלש? u'mah ra'isa l'rabos ba'alas chamesh
u'lehotzi ba'alas shalosh? Why are we including a five-cornered garment and excluding
a three-cornered one? That'd be obvious. מרבה אני בעלת חמש שיש בכלל
חמש ארבע. Marbe ani ba'alas chamesh sheyesh bikhlal chamesh arba. I include
five because five also has four.
ומוציא אני בעלת שלש שאין בכלל שלש ארבע. u'motzi ani ba'alas shalosh
she'ein bikhlal shalosh arba. Three doesn't include four. So anyway, אשר תכסה
בה asher t'khasse bah comes to include even if it's not exactly
four, even if it's a five-cornered garment, but they do not exclude
anything having to do with whether it can be seen. ורבי שמעון,
V'Rabbi Shimon, where does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon get to include a
five-cornered garment? מאשר נפקא. m'asher nafka. The extra אשר, asher, it should
have said תכסה בה t'khasse bah I guess. So that includes both
a garment of a blind person and five corners. ורבנן אשר לא
משמע להו. V'Rabanan asher lo mashma lehu. And the Rabbis are not
impressed by אשר. asher. Okay, so now we have a debate whether
ציצית tzitzis are limited to only day garments. And as I said
before, there's a debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Does that mean daytime
or does it mean day garments? And the obvious difference is if
I'm going to wear my ציצית tzitzis now at night and I
put them on, a) should I wear them? I say this is
basically a day garment, let me go ahead and do this מצוה.
mitzvah. Or no, should I say since it's night time, it's not
a מצוה, mitzvah, maybe if I'm trying to do a מצוה mitzvah
it's בל תוסיף bal tosif or whatever, certainly I have no need
to do it. And number two, if I do put on ציצית
tzitzis at night, do I make a ברכה bracha of להתעטף בציצית
l'hisatef b'tzitzis or על מצות ציצית? al mitzvas tzitzis? Is it about
daytime or is it about day garment? That's a סוגיא sugya in
the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara says כסות יום, khsuso yom, so
sounds like it's a garment. But anyway, there's a debate in the
ראשונים. Rishonim. How do we פסקן pasken the exclusion of night? Do
we פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that night is excluded?
We do פסקן pasken that women are exempt in ציצית. tzitzis. And
the question is what do we mean by night? Night time or
night garments? We obviously say either way. So if you happen to
have pajamas that have four corners and you put ציצית tzitzis on
them, don't make the ברכה bracha when you get up in the
morning and put on your pajamas if you decide to wear pajamas
during the day. More significantly, if you put on your ציצית tzitzis
at night, don't make a ברכה bracha because it might not be
about the garment, it might be about the night.
But if you have pajamas, you wouldn't put on ציצית tzitzis to
begin with. We're saying כסות לילה. khsuso layla.
No, well we would because
we have a חומרא chumra basically.
But you wouldn't make a ברכה bracha on it when you put
on ציצית. tzitzis. Right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ורבנן האי וראיתם אתו מאי עבדי ליה? V'Rabanan hai u're'isem oso
mai avdi lei? So what do they do with the וראיתם אתו
u're'isem oso since it's not coming to exclude night time or blind
people? And now the גמרא Gemara. finally shifts into more of the,
if you will, you know, agadic, religious discussion of ציצית. tzitzis. מבעי
ליה לכדתניא, mibayei lei l'khid'tanya, like we learned in the ברייתא, braisa,
וראיתם אתו וזכרתם, u're'isem oso u'zkhartem, you shall see it and remember.
ראה מצוה זו וזכור מצוה אחרת. Re'eh mitzvah zo u'zkhor mitzvah acheres.
See this and remember another מצוה. mitzvah. What מצוה mitzvah is it?
התלויה בה, hatluyah bah, which is dependent in it. ואיזו זו? v'eizo
zo? קריאת שמע. Krias Shema. It's קריאת שמע. Krias Shema. So you
think about the ציצית tzitzis and you remember the שמע, Shema, כל
מצות ה'. kol mitzvos Hashem. And why? דתנן, d'tnan, מאימתי קורין את
שמע בשחרית? me'eimasai korin es Shema b'shacharis? מאימתי קורין את שמע... Me'eimasai
korin es Shema... קריאת שמע בשחרית krias shema b’shacharis כשיכיר בין תכלת
ללבן, k’sheyakir bein tcheles l’lavan, so because the way you know what
it's time to say שמע shema is when you can see between
the white and the blue of strands of your ציצית, tzitzis, so
ציצית tzitzis is the שמע shema depends on ציצית. tzitzis. Now of
course that's only like rabbinic to use that as the שיעור. shiur.
תוספות goes even further. תוספות says that where שמע shema according to
some opinions the entire שמע shema is rabbinic, so it can't be
פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. Nevertheless, it reflects the attitude towards
שמע shema which should also be thought about in some of the
attitude towards תפילין and מזוזה. mezuzah. These פרשיות parshiyos are כל מצוות
ה׳. kol mitzvos Hashem. Right? What does it say by ציצית? tzitzis?
וראיתם אותו וזכרתם את כל מצוות ה׳. ur’item oto uzachartem et kol
mitzvos Hashem. And the thinking about the פרשיות parshiyos in the מזוזה
mezuzah and the פרשיות parshiyos in תפילין as a distillation of הכל
כולה. hakol kulah. ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד, Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad, right,
and keeping the מצוות, mitzvos, right, and same about the other two
פרשיות parshiyos in תפילין as why are we doing all these מצוות?
mitzvos? זכר ליציאת מצרים. zecher l’yetzias mitzrayim. So that is like the
essence of the תורה, Torah this beautiful article that I'd put up
on the web but I hadn't had a chance to read by
this Rabbi Yosef Nagen, who talks about some of the symbolism of
תפילין. And he points out that תפילין, you know, was considered could
have been considered like a mini ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. He has
some proofs for that and, you know, that that's also why for
example, you know, maybe that they included the עשרת הדיברות Aseres Hadibros
in those קומראן Qumran תפילין in it as a mini ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. Also because the פרשה parsha of שמע shema which is,
you know, ודברת בם בשבתך בביתך ובלכתך בדרך, v’dibarta bam b’shivtecha b’veitecha
uv’lechtecha vaderech, it's probably talking about the עשרת הדיברות Aseres Hadibros that
preceded it, not just self-referential.
But then he goes further and says that therefore when you have
a some of these אגדות aggadotas that speak about any person that
says that has ציצית על בגדו, tzitzis al bigdo, תפילין בראשו, tefillin
b’rosho,
וספר תורה בזרועו, v’Sefer Torah b’zro’o, וציצית בבגדו v’tzitzis b’vigdo is מובטח
לו שלא יחטא. muvtach lo shelo yecheta. He says ספר תורה בזרועו
Sefer Torah b’zro’o means תפילין של יד. tefillin shel yad. It doesn't
mean literally you're holding a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. That that was
referred to as a type of a ספר תורה בזרועו, Sefer Torah
b’zro’o, which I thought was a great פשט. pshat. Anyway, so here
the גמרא saying that you see the ציצית tzitzis and you remember
כל מצוות ה׳, kol mitzvos Hashem, you're remembering the שמע, shema, which
is essentially כל מצוות ה׳, kol mitzvos Hashem, which is also within
the תפילין. Anyway, the גמרא emphasizes it because of the blue and
the white of the is the time you start saying שמע, shema,
so ציצית tzitzis and שמע shema are naturally intertwined, excuse the pun.
Okay. So the גמרא says like that.
Okay. וכי תימא. v’chi teima. Fine. דתניא אידך, detanya idach, וראיתם אותו
וזכרתם, ur’item oto uzachartem, ראה מצוה זו וזכור מצוה אחרת. re’eh mitzvah
zo u’zchor mitzvah acheret. See this מצוה mitzvah and remember another מצוה
mitzvah הסמוכה לה, hasmucha lah, the one that's juxtaposed it. ואיזו זו
מצות כלאים. v’eizo zo mitzvas kilayim. כלאים כתיב, kilayim kesiv, וסמוך ליה
שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו. v’samuch leih shatnez tzemer u’fishtim yachdav. Don't wear
שעטנז, shatnez, you know, wool and linen together. גדילים תעשה לך gedilim
ta’aseh lach and do ציצית. tzitzis.
So that's obviously not as so, okay. The whole point of ציצית
tzitzis is to remember כלאים. kilayim. Maybe it's to tell you, you
know, be careful about ציצית, tzitzis, don't let it lead into slippery
slope and into you being over on שעטנז shatnez in other places
although we allow you to do ציצית tzitzis when, you know, שעטנז
shatnez when you are wearing ציצית. tzitzis.
Although the רבנן we
even forbade that although this depends whether that was just בית שמאי
Beis Shammai and if we פסקן pasken that גמרא. But then if
read that way, it's sort of to say, you know, part of
the other way of sort of then seeing this is what are
you supposed to be remembering? Are you supposed to be remembering the
עשה’s aseh and the לא תעשה’s lo sa’aseh is another way of
seeing this. Like is the idea here be careful, make protections, watch
that you don't
transgress, you know, when you go out into the world. Because the
way I sort of hold the whole idea of ציצית tzitzis is
it's on your בגד, beged, you're going out into the world and
you're looking at your ציצית tzitzis and you're remembering your obligations. So
in what way are you remembering your obligations? Are you remembering your
obligation to sort of bring תורה into the world and bring godliness
and bring מצוות mitzvos into the world or are you remembering your
obligation that like, you know, watch out, there are a lot of
עבירות aveiras out there, be careful. So anyway I see that that's
a little bit of a difference between whether you're thinking about the
שמע shema or you're thinking about the כלאים. kilayim. Okay, what are
we sort of supposed to be remembering?
Or as if to say take it simply וזכרתם את כל מצוות
ה׳, uzachartem et kol mitzvos Hashem, every time, you know, like you,
I understand.
You can't think about everything at once. So there's certain things that
symbolize it. Alright, תניא אידך, tanya idach, וראיתם אותו וזכרתם. ur’item oto
uzachartem.
Now we get fully into the וזכרתם, v’zachartem, you shall see them
and remember him. וראיתם אותו וזכרתם את כל מצוות ה׳. ur’item oto
uzachartem et kol mitzvos Hashem. שכיון שנתחייב אדם במצוה זו נתחייב בכל
המצוות כולן. shekeivan shenitchayev adam b’mitzvah zo nitchayev b’chol hamitzvos kulan. Once
you're חייב chayav in this מצוה mitzvah you're חייב chayav in all
the מצוות. mitzvos. Meaning, so what does that mean? רבי שמעון היא
דאמר מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא היא. Rebbi Shimon hi d’amar mitzvas aseh
shehazman grama hi. It's Rebbi Shimon says it's a positive מצוה mitzvah
that time is bound, because what does that mean? It means that
oh if you're חייב chayav in this you're חייב chayav in everything.
So once you get to be בר מצוה’d Bar Mitzvah and you're
חייב chayav in ציצית tzitzis you're חייב chayav in all the מצוות.
mitzvos. Well that only is true if we're talking about men. But
if we're talking about women and women are חייב chayav in ציצית,
tzitzis, then when women get to be obligated in ציצית tzitzis they're
not obligated in all the מצוות, mitzvos, they're מצוות mitzvos they remain
exempt from. So the idea is that with this comes all of
the other מצוות mitzvos is only true about men who are fully
obligated in all of the מצוות. mitzvos. But for women even if
they're obligated in ציצית tzitzis they're not obligated in the other מצוות.
mitzvos. So this would be רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon who says that
we are talking that we're only talking about men. Okay,
now
תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא, Baraisa, וראיתם אותו
וזכרתם את כל מצוות ה׳. ur’item oto uzachartem et kol mitzvos Hashem.
שקולה מצוה זו כנגד כל המצוות כולן. shekulah mitzvah zo k’neged kol
hamitzvos kulan. This is equivalent to all the other מצוות, mitzvos, which,
you know, that doesn't literally mean it, but again it's this is
reminding you of all the other מצוות. mitzvos. So it has that
sort of symbolic weight. תניא אידך *Tanya idach*, we've done another ברייתא
*Baraita*, וראיתם אותו וזכרתם ועשיתם *Ur'item oto uzchartem va'asitem*. So that this
is just straight פירוש *peirush* of the word, you'll see the מצוות
*mitzvot*, you'll remember and then you'll do them, ועשיתם אותם *va'asitem otam*.
ראייה מביאה לידי זכירה *Re'iyah mevi'ah lidei zechirah*, seeing something reminds you
of the thing that it represents. Seeing leads to remembering, וזכירה מביאה
לידי עשייה *uzechirah mevi'ah lidei asiyah*,
and remembering brings you to actually do. And it's actually interesting because
the famous דרשה *drasha* of חז"ל Chazal, *Chazal* at the end of
פרשת ציצית tzitzit *parashat tzitzit* is ולא תתורו אחרי לבבכם ואחרי עיניכם
אשר אתם זונים אחריהם *Velo taturu acharei levavchem ve'acharei eineichem asher atem
zonim achareihem*, which they say that העיניים והלב הם סרסורי עבירה *ha'einayim
vehalev hem sirsurei aveirah*, that we only sin because our eyes and
our heart sort of are like middlemen to the sin. They like,
we see something, we desire it, and that leads us to sin.
So the actual ציצית tzitzit, *tzitzit* is, you know, it's sort of
saying you don't just סתם *stam* do מצוות *mitzvot*, you don't just
סתם *stam* sin. Something has to spark that in you. So the
ציצית tzitzit. *tzitzit* should spark remembering your מצוות *mitzvot* of God and
doing them. ראייה מביאה לידי זכירה זכירה מביאה לידי עשייה *Re'iyah mevi'ah
lidei zechirah zechirah mevi'ah lidei asiyah*, as opposed to the opposite, you
know, ולא תתורו אחרי לבבכם ואחרי עיניכם *velo taturu acharei levavchem ve'acharei
eineichem*. You see all of the things that are desirable out there
in the world and that sparks in you the desire and that
then sparks into you the action. So there's a nice little sort
of parallel about how what you see affects what you desire, affects
how you're going to be motivated and what you're going to do.
מהא פטור *Me'ha patur*, right? He won't see, he won't desire? Could
be.
There you go.
There you go. Okay. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר *Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai omer*, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says, כל הזהיר במצוה זו זוכה
ומקבל פני שכינה *kol hazahir bemitzvah zo zocheh umekabel pnei Shechinah*. If
you're careful this מצוה *mitzvah*, you will indeed receive the Divine Presence.
כתיב הכא וראיתם אותו וכתיב התם את ה' אלקיך תירא ואותו תעבוד
*Ketiv hacha ur'item oto uchtiv hatam et Hashem Elokecha tira ve'oto ta'avod*.
You will see God, so see
אותו *oto* as to fear God?
Yeah, I think it's how it's reading it. It's reading it as
not fear, but that's what I believe how the גמרא *Gemara* is
reading it. Okay. So anyway, and seeing it is not necessarily just
seeing the תכלת *techeilet*, but seeing God. Okay. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*,
our rabbis taught, חביבין ישראל chavivin Yisrael
*chavivin Yisrael*, how dear is Israel, שסיבבן הקדוש ברוך הוא במצוות *shesivvan
Hakadosh Baruch Hu
bemitzvot*.
God surrounded them with מצוות *mitzvot*. תפילין בראשיהם ותפילין בזרועיהם *Tefillin berasheihem
utefillin bizro'eihem*, תפילין *tefillin* on their heads and on their arms. וציצית
בבגדיהם *Vetzitzit bevigdeihem*, and ציצית tzitzit *tzitzit* on their garments. ומזוזה לפתחיהם
*Umezuzah lepitcheihem*, and a מזוזה mezuzah *mezuzah* on their door. ועליהם אמר
דוד *Ve'aleihem amar David*, and regarding them David said, שבע ביום הללתיך
על משפטי צדקך *Sheva bayom hillalticha al mishpetei tzidkecha*. I praise you
God for seven things for your just laws. What are the seven?
Four corners of the ציצית tzitzit *tzitzit*, the two תפילין *tefillin*, and
the one מזוזה *mezuzah* is seven. ובשעה שנכנס דוד לבית המרחץ *Uvesha'ah
shenichnas David leveit hamerchatz*, when David went into the bathhouse, וראה עצמו
עומד ערום *vera'ah atzmo omed arum*, and arum, arom, arum, arum, arum.
Arum is crafty,
arum is naked.
Arum, okay, he
saw himself standing naked, אמר אוי לי שאעמוד ערום בלא מצוה *amar
oy li she'e'emod arum belo mitzvah*. He said, woe is me that
I'm standing naked without מצוות *mitzvot*. Thank you. וכיון שנזכר במילה שבבשרו
*Vekeivan shenizkar bamilah shebevesaro*, then he remembered, oh wait, the ברית מילה
*brit milah* that's inscribed in his flesh, נתיישבה דעתו *nityashvah da'ato*,
he felt comforted or settled. ואחר שיצא *Ve'achar sheyatzah*, after he left
because you can't talk תורה *Torah* in the bathroom, אמר *amar*, he
said. And then we have what we had before. Right. He said
song, שנאמר shenemar, למנצח על השמינית מזמור לדוד *shene'emar lamenatze'ach al hashminit
mizmor ledavid*. For the on the eighth. The eighth because you had
the seven מצוות *mitzvot*, the ציצית *tzitzit*, תפילין *tefillin*, whatever, and this
is the eighth. And also that מילה *milah* is on the eighth
day. So למנצח על השמינית מזמור לדוד על המילה שניתנה בשמינית *Lamenatze'ach
al hashminit mizmor ledavid al hamilah shenitnah bashminit*. From the מילה *milah*
that was given on the eighth. רש"י *Rashi*, בשמינית *bashminit*,
meaning to be done on the eighth. And the מהרש"א *Maharsha* also
points out that it was the eighth מצוה *mitzvah* given to the
world because you had the seven מצוות בני נח *mitzvot bnei Noach*
and the מילה *milah* was the eighth.
But that I don't think is for everyone.
Well, that's a question of the פלוגתא דבני נח *plugta debnei Noach*.
Anyway, so that's the point.
But the real point here is, I think, while it starts about
that God was מסבב אותם *mesovev otam*, like God loves them so
he surrounded them and maybe it talks about thinking about God, I
think what it quickly moved to is the idea about clothing as
identity. Right? And that's why, now true, you do have the מזוזה
בפתחיהם *mezuzah bepitcheihem*, but that also sort of is about the identity
of the house, the Jewish house. You know, but I think that
whole point is that David is saying if I don't have these
things to define me as Jewish, right, what does that mean? I'm
ערום בלא מצוות *arum belo mitzvot*. Where's my Jewish identity, you know,
in a sort of physical way? And then the ברית מילה *brit
milah* is, no, no, no, it's inscribed in my flesh. Of course,
what about this why if Rivka were here, we'd have a nice
long discussion, but you'd be right, you know, what is this saying
about women? It's not that women are exempt from all over these.
Presumably to reach in a more a healthier a bigger debate about,
they are חייב *chayav* in מזוזה *mezuzah*, but certainly not this whole
complement in terms of identity, and it's not inscribed in their flesh.
You know, so what is that sort of saying about women? I
think is an important question. But at least, you know, what's I
think the importance about this is it's not just a lot of
מצוות *mitzvot*. It's מצוות *mitzvot* that very much sort of define your
identity and then this idea about the ברית מילה *brit milah*. Let's
just read a little bit more about that.
רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב
Rebbi
Eliezer
Ben Yaakov *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*...
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב says, כל שיש
לו תפילין בראשו ותפילין בזרועו וציצית בבגדו ומזוזה בפתחו. kol sheyeish lo
tefillin berosho utefillin bizro'o vetzitzit bevigdo umezuzah befitcho. So
again, you're wearing your תפילין and your ציצית and you have your
מזוזה, הכל בחיזוק, hakol bechizuk, it all with asurity,
שלא יחטא, shelo yecheta, it's certain you won't sin. שנאמר והחוט המשולש
לא
במהרה ינתק—the shenemar vehachut hameshulash lo bimehera yinatek three-bound string, ציצית, תפילין,
and מזוזה will not easily break. This will protect you from sin.
So here there is this shift from identity and חביבין ישראל and
the way of marking us as related to God, which was the
previous theme, to saying that these are protecting us from sin. They
remind us of our obligations and they protect us from sin. Okay,
אומר חנה מלאך ה' סביב ליראיו ויחלצם, omer choneh malach Hashem saviv
liyre'av vayechaltzem,
the angel of God protects them and protects them from sin. That's
the רמב"ם by מזוזה. The רמב"ם says what's protecting you about the
מזוזה is not its magical powers and not some angels, but basically
the fact that it serves as a reminder to protect you against
sin.
Right, and this is a very easy way for people to think
that the מזוזה is now more of an amulet, like we were
getting before, חז"ל, you know.
But the point is here that it's not. No, no, I understand.
These inhibit that shift. I know, which is exactly the problem. תניא
היה רבי מאיר אומר מה נשתנה תכלת מכל מיני צבעונין, Tanya, hayah
Rebbi Meir omer, mah nishtanah techeilet mikol minei tzeva'onim, why is תכלת
different from all other colors? מפני שהתכלת דומה לים וים דומה לרקיע,
mipnei shehatecheilet domeh layam veyam domeh larakia,
it's like the ocean and the ocean is like the sky, ורקיע
לכסא הכבוד, verakia lekise hakevod, and that's like the heaven. So it's
different degrees of blue, but eventually through many derivations, it's similar to
the blue of—that's the point, the כסא הכבוד. Kise Hakevod. שנאמר, I
understand, ותחת רגליו כמעשה לבנת
הספיר—under vetaht raglav kema'aseh livnat hasappir God's legs is like the sapphire
stone—וכעצם השמים לטהר—like uke'etzem hashamayim latohar the sort of the essence of
the heaven. וכתיב כמראה אבן
ספיר דמות כסא. u'ktiv kemareh even sappir demut kisei. So this לבנת
הספיר livnat hasappir which you're assuming means light—I understand—no,
this ספיר sappir which is like the heavens is this ספיר sappir
of God's כסא הכבוד. Kise Hakevod. So something that is similar to
the color of heavens is also similar to the כסא הכבוד. Kise
Hakevod. So obviously, as Michael says, it is by derivation. It's not
like this blue is directly like the כסא הכבוד. Kise Hakevod. It's
like one blue which is like another, which is like another, eventually
it's like the כסא הכבוד. Kise Hakevod. But, and we'll end here,
but I did want to say one other point about this. It's
not just that. I saw again a beautiful explanation, had some time
on my hand on יום טוב, Yom Tov, so I was looking
around, and I דאוונד davened in a כולל kollel which was great
because then I could just learn. So anyway, so the קרן אורה
Keren Orah says, this is a beautiful idea. He says, here's the
idea. The idea is not just eventually we think about God. Oh,
we're thinking about God. The idea is that we're thinking about God
by look—you look at the—when you look at the ים, yam, you
know, you sort of see that that's a blue that's similar to
the כסא הכבוד. Kise Hakevod. It also works in the reverse: once
it links all up, it also links down from God. So the
ים yam ultimately relates to God and the שמים shamayim relate to
God and the whole world relates to God. So it leads to
you seeing God in every aspect of the natural world and in
every aspect of the world. And so that's what he sort of
sees as—not just makes you think about God, but since you got
there through the world, it also makes you see God throughout the
world. And I do think that that again, I see a tension
here going on between the ציצית. Is the ציצית about how do
we engage the world or how do we protect ourselves when we
go out into the world? Is it about being afraid about כלאים
kilayim or is it about remembering מצוות ה'? mitzvot Hashem? Is it
about sort of that these are things that protect me from sin?
Right?
שנאמר והחוט המשולש לא במהרה ינתק—protect shenemar vehachut hameshulash lo bimehera yinatek
me from sin—or are these the things that sort of strengthen my
Jewish identity, but hopefully that's more in a positive way and brings
me out into the world? So I think that that
question, ציצית as sort of as clothing, as identity, and as about
whether it's about a protection or whether it's about a strong identity
to engage the world, at least to me I see those as
two different themes that are sort of in tension here. Okay, we'll
end with that.